Okay, folks. Uh, can you hear my voice
clearly?
Yes. No.
All right. So, we're going to continue
our sequence of lectures on record
neural networks. Today, we'll talk about
stability analysis and LSTMs.
So the story so far is that iterated
structures are good for analyzing time
series data with short time dependence
on the past. Iterated structures are
structures like convolutional neural
networks or time delay neural networks.
However, if you want long-term
dependence into the infinite past, then
you want recurrent structures and these
are what we call recurrent neural
networks.
Now, recreate neural networks were
introduced as a mechanism for uh
modeling time series data, but as it
turns out, they're good for other things
as well. Things that you don't associate
uh recurrence with. So, here's a simple
problem for you. I want to build a
regular conventional MLP that can add
two binary digit numbers and give you
the result. So the two numbers are both
n bits each and every entries are one or
a zero and the output must be the sum of
the two also in binary. If I just want
to construct a regular MLP, how large is
this MLP going to be? Anyone?
How large would this line is this MLP
going to be?
Anywhere.
So 2N
is it going to be 2N? How this MLP has
to capture every possible addition of
two n bit numbers? How large will it be
inside? Anyone?
Take a guess. Take a guess.
2 n * n
2 n it's going to be exponentially sized
because you want to capture every
possible combination of input bits.
Right? Now even if it were not
exponentially sized now if I want to
learn this network so that whenever I
give you two n bit numbers it gives you
that binary result. How many different
training instances must I provide it to
ensure that it learns every single
addition? Anyone?
How many patterns must I provide it?
To ensure that it learns the right
thing.
What do you think?
Yes. To ensure all of them,
it's going to require 2 to two n, right?
Because to make sure that every single
combination is accounted for, there are
two raised to two n combinations because
there are n bits here and n bits here.
And this is the number of training
instances that you would have to see to
actually learn this network and be sure
that it has learned everything.
Even if you manage to do that, if I want
to now add two n +1 bit numbers, this
network can no longer do it. Now, this
is using a simple MLP. If I were to do
this using just an RNN,
then here's what I can do. I can use
this simple unit which just adds things
one bit at a time and it just so at each
point it adds one bit from A, one bit
from B, generates the result and the
carry. That's all it does.
This can this be used to add two n bit
numbers.
This little network
yes or no.
How many neurons does it have?
It's just going to learn four simple
patterns, right? If both bits are zero
and previous carries a zero, it's going
to need eight patterns, right? So you
have eight patterns. 0 0 1
0 0 1 0
0 1 1. So this is the previous carry.
This is bit one
bit. And this is the bit from the second
number, bit two. And you have eight of
these, right? 1 0 0 1 0 1 1 1 0
1 1 1 and in response to each of these
there's an output carry and an output
bit. So there be two numbers. These
would be both zero. It's going to be 0
and one and so on. Right? So it only
needs to learn these many patterns. How
many neurons will it require?
No more than eight. Right? And in fact
far fewer. How many training instances
will it require to ensure that it's
learned everything? Anybody?
How many training instances will it
require?
Come on, guys. Answer is staring staring
you in the face.
Are you guys here?
Eight. Just eight, right? There are only
eight combinations. If you just saw
these eight combinations, you know every
possible way of uh every possible input
combination and what the output must be.
So as you can see just going from a flat
MLP to a recurrent structure reduce the
size of the network and the amount of
training data required by a massive
massive massive amount even for the
small problem. Moreover, there's no
limit on the number of bits in the input
that can be added inputs that can be
added. Here's another problem, right? I
just want the parity. I want the this I
want to train an MLP which looks at an N
bit input and gives me the parity. Now
the parity as you so know is either even
or odd. So if the number of ones here is
even the output is zero. The number of
ones here is odd the output is one.
Right? So or the other way around. So
how many training instances will I need
if I want to train an MLP of this kind?
Anyone?
How many training instances will I need?
I'm going to need all two race to two
end training instances to ensure that
this MLP is completely learns to give
the correct output for every pattern.
Right? And how large is the MLP itself?
This is an exor. So it's going to need
something like R3 and neurons.
Nonetheless, the number of training
instances is going to be very large. If
I did this with recurrence where I just
have the previous output and the latest
bit going in and if both are the same,
then the output is zero. If both are
different, the output is one. Can this
be used to compute the parity also?
Observe that anytime I get a one, the
parity flips. Otherwise, the parity
stays the same. Right? How many training
instances will I need for this one?
How many training instances am I going
to need for this?
They're just two, right? The previous
input, the current input. So 0 0 1 1 0 1
1, right?
and that that gives me the whole uh uh
training set that I need for training
this model. So once again
what required an exponential amount of
training data using a flat MLP
could be solved using a recurrent
network using a fraction a logarithmic
fraction of that amount of training
data. Did this make sense to everybody?
the power of recurrence. Does this make
sense to everybody? Right? And so
recurren neural networks are not just
magic for time series. They're a very
powerful tool. If you know how to apply
them, you can apply them to all kinds of
problems where they can give you a
massive advantage. So here's our first
poll.
15 seconds, guys.
All right, let me stop this in one, two,
three.
Okay.
So,
what is the answer to the first
question?
True or false? True and true. That's
right. Both are true. Some prediction
and classification problems that require
very large MLPS and a large amount of
training data can be solved using small
recurrent networks that only require
small amounts of training data. So this
is not just for MLPS. It's also true for
convolutional neural networks.
That stated
so we know what a recurren network is
and we know how powerful it can get. We
also saw how it can be trained. they can
be trained by minimizing the divergence
between the sequence of outputs it
generates and a desired sequence of
outputs through gradient descent or back
propagation.
So let's go back and analyze how these
networks work. Now consider the simple
time delay neural network. I have the
network which looks at four inputs and
computer computes its output. And assume
for another assume that all the
activations are uh we're going to use
something like a sigmoid or a tanh or a
relu. Now if the inputs are all bounded,
can the output ever explode and go to
infinity? All the inputs are bounded.
Can the output go to infinity?
Yes or no?
What do you guys think?
I see one. No. Can I get a two? Okay,
that's it. Only two people are convinced
that it's enough. What about the rest of
you guys? Do you think it can go to
infinity?
Like three, four. Okay,
that's that's slow. But it can't, right?
Because there's no operation over here
that that's going to exclude the
numbers. If the inputs are bounded, the
output is bounded. This is what is
called a bounded input bounded output
network. It's called it's the network is
stable. If the input is bounded, the
output is also bounded. It's bible
stable. This is a highly desirable
characteristic.
But then look at this recurrent network.
Will this recurrent network be
necessarily viable as well? Meaning if
the inputs are all bounded, will the
output also be bounded? What do you guys
think?
Yes or no?
over here.
Not necessarily. Okay. But you have to
be careful. If all the output and hidden
activations are bounded like a sigmoid
or a tanh, then the output is not when
the overall output is not going to blow
up. But it can saturate and always give
you a one which will which is
meaningless.
uh but because it carries no information
but
it's going to give you useless answers.
Now to understand when it will actually
give you use useful answers we have to
look at a simpler version of the model
where we only consider linear
activations. What happens along this
hidden layer and because all the
recurrence is only in this hidden layer
it's sufficient for us to analyze what
happens over here. Okay. And we're going
to be assuming a linear activation
because a linear act assuming that we
work in the linear uh the in the linear
domain of the inputs then a linear
activation kind of captures what
actually happens inside the network
and also it's just easier to analyze
linear linear models. So we're using the
street light effect again over here. So
here's the model that we have. We have
this recurrent network. We're going to
assume that in this hidden layer the
activation function is an identity
function. Meaning you first compute the
aphine term and the output is just the
aine term itself. So f of z equals z. We
are assuming the simple
linear activation. This clear as an
assumption as a second sense.
Yes. Now
can I see some thumbs up guy? Thumbs ups
guys if you don't want to type. Maybe 10
thumbs ups before I proceed.
Okay, fine. So, this is what I'm going
to use. Okay. And let's see how this
behaves.
So, here is my network. If Z= W * HTT=
W * HT - 1 + WH
* HT - 1 + WX XT and HTT= ZT, meaning
there's no activation function. That's
the same as writing this guy, right?
You're saying h I'm using the index k
over here is w * h k minus 1 + wx xx k.
So this is now our recurrent neuron.
Right? Now using the same
formula hkus1 in turn was wh * hkus 2
plus wx xkus1. Right? So if I want to
write HK in terms of HK minus 2, what
would I do? I just stick this guy in
here, right? And if I replace this term
with this formula, I get the whole thing
uh in terms of uh HK minus one. So let's
see what that looks like. If I stick it
here, I'm going to get HK
equals
WH.
That's this WH
times this term which gives me WH 2
HKUS 2
plus
WH
wx
K - 1.
So this is taken care of plus
wx
X K. So, did this equation make sense? I
just plugged in this value in here. So,
did this make sense to everybody what I
just did? Okay. Yes. No. I got one yes.
Did this make sense to you guys?
Guys, I'm very tired. Please be
responsive. Okay.
Otherwise, I'll just go on and I won't
really bother about your responses.
Don't put me in that spot. So, now
that's what we got. WH HK = WX^2 HK -2 +
WHx WX XK - 1 plus WXX K. But then I
have the same formula, right? HK - 2,
what was HKUS 2? HKUS 2 is going to be
WH
HKUS 3, right? plus
wx
x
k
uh - 2, right?
And so now I can plug this formula over
here and now I'm explain writing down hk
in terms of hkus 3. And if you work it
out, that's going to be whubed
* hkus 3
+ w^
squar
time wx
x kus 2
and so on. So did this make sense that
this is the same as this guy? Yes or no?
Yes. No.
Okay.
And so continuing on with that, if I
just expand it out and push it all the
way till I'm only left with H of -1,
we're going to be left with this
formula. HK is whis to x kus one. X k +
1 * h of -1. This is the initial value.
We can assume for analysis sake that h
of -1 is zero plus w raised to k wxx0
plus w ra to k -1 wxx1 and so on. So the
sum of this index and this index is
going to be k in every case. Did this
formula make sense?
Did this make sense? It's okay. over
here this term is the response to a
single input at time x time zero. This
term is the response to the input at
time one and so on. So I can write the
whole thing like so right this is the
response to an input at time z when
there are no other inputs and zero
initial conditions. So if I write the
whole thing out, if I write h k of x0,
this is the response at time k to an
input at time z. So if I have a series
of inputs
and if I look at the output at this
time, if the response to this input
blows up and begins becomes infinity,
then the overall system is going to is
blowing up. If the response to this
input does not blow up, these guys are
closer to where I am. So it means that
these guys have also not blown up. And
so it's sufficient for me to look at
this guy to decide if the network is
going to blow up. It's the output of the
network is going to blow up or not. That
make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Okay. So that's what I'm going to do,
right? I'm just going to be looking at
this. What happens to a single input at
time zero? Does this make the network
blow up or not? Now the point of
recurrence was to hold things on in
memory. Right? So if I have some input
over here at time zero, ideally this
thing must be kept in memory until it's
no longer needed. Right? So the hidden
state must neither blow up nor fade but
somehow carry x0. But let's see what
happens. I have this guy. My formula was
ht was wh
plus c of xt. Right? So working my way
back if I write htus 1 as w * htus 2 and
so on the overall response you you'll
find is simply that the time response at
time t to an input at time 0 is simply w
ra to t * x0. Is this making sense?
You can see this easily enough by
writing this equals w ^2
htus 1
plus something tus 1 and this is going
to be w cub htus 2. Eventually you're
going to be left with w to t * x0. So
this make sense to everybody?
This one? Yes. Okay. When will it blow
up with time? When will it blow up?
When will the When will this blow up
guys?
Will it blow up?
If w is greater than, this thing is
going to blow up, right? If w is less
than one, what happens?
If w is less than one, what happens?
It's going to go to zero. Okay, guys.
I'm not getting a fast enough response.
I'm tired. I'm just going to move on. If
you want to respond please do otherwise
it's okay right and so what happens here
is that the response of the system blows
up if w is greater than one and falls to
zero if w is less than one in either
case it no longer retains information
about x0 because the thing has either
died or just exploded this is for a
scalar what if I work with vectors right
if I work with vectors then w is a
matrix
same thing holds H0 of T the response at
time T to an input at time Z is going to
be W raised to T * CX0
I can write this matrix W using
decomposition as U lambda U inverse U
are the igon vectors lambda the is the
igon value matrix which is diagonal and
so w ra to t in this case is simply
going to be u lambda u inverse * u
lambda u inverse and so on so these
things just become I and you're left
with U * lambda to T * U inverse which
is just U * the IG value matrix all the
values raised to T * U inverse. If I
pull out this this guy if I assume that
the values are all arranged in in order
of decreasing value. So lambda 1 is the
largest value. I can rewrite this as
lambda 1 raised to t * u * this matrix
time u inverse. Did this make sense
what I just did?
Yes or no? Right? And so
if I write this like so then here is
what I have right this guy is going to
be
w ra to t cx0 is going to be this term
time x0.
Yes. Was that a question?
>> Yeah.
>> Yes. Uh why why are HTS negative? I I
didn't get that.
>> But why why are HDs
>> negative?
>> Where are they negative?
It's h of t minus one. Current t minus
one is the previous term. That's it.
>> Yeah. The the the current one in the
left left hand side. It's negative h of
t and negative h z of t. Where did I see
I don't see any negative sign here.
>> Yeah,
>> that is just a dash to represent.
>> That's that's an
>> that's the bullet that PowerPoint put.
Please erase that thing, guys. Okay. All
right. So, that's this PowerPoint. So,
here you have it, right? This is the
largest value. If this value is greater
than one, this guy is going to blow up.
If this igen value is less than one,
this guy is going to this guy is going
to die to zero. In either case, the
uh actual value that you're trying to
remember x0 is forgotten, right? So
here's some here's an example here. I
have some random w matrix and I have the
same recussion that I had earlier. I
have a this is this is this is for
fourdimensional vectors. If I have a
single input which is all once at time
zero. In this case the largest value of
W is 0.9. You can see that the responses
for just die to zero. Right here I've
got two different values. One is for
0.9. The other is a different one. Uh
here I have a W where W is where the
largest value is 1.1 and this is the
largest value is one. You can see when
the value largest value is 1.1 it blows
up. If it's one, it kind of just stays
around, right? These two are the same.
In one case, I see some oscillation, and
the other I don't. Can you take sort of
can you take a guess as to why you you
see this kind of oscillating behavior in
this example, but not here? Anyone?
Why would that be?
Well,
make the mess, you know, uh suspense
values can be real or they can be
complex conjugate pairs. So in these two
cases you have complex conjugate pair
values. So it doesn't go up smoothly. It
oscillates. Nonetheless, if the largest
value is less than one, the magnitude is
less than one, the thing dies. If here
the largest value is greater than one,
it blows up. If it's one, it stays
stable. Right?
So you have it. The only time when uh
the uh system is holds what it's
supposed to be in memory is if all the
igon values not just the largest are
equal to one otherwise uh only the
components that lie along the igon
vectors with the igon value one will be
held stable all the others will die
and so in linear systems long-term
behavior depends entirely on the igen
values of the recurrent weight matrix.
If the largest value is greater than
one, the system blows up. If it's lesser
than one, the response vanishes very
quickly. Complex values can cause
oscilly response, but are the same
overall trends. And the rate of blow up
or vanishing depends only on the igen
values and not on the input. So how long
you remember something doesn't depend on
what you're trying to remember, just
depends on the weight matrix matrix.
And that's with a linear activation,
right? What happens if I have a
nonlinear activation? If I have a
nonlinear activation, here's an example
with sigmoid activations. Same thing.
These are for scalers. These plots are
crazy, but they're not that crazy. I
have consider each column considers a
different input. Here the input at time
0 is minus.5. There are no further
inputs. Here the input at time 0 is 0.
Here it's 0.5.
There are two parameters the weight and
the bias. So here the weights are 0.9 1
and 1.1 within each there are five
pictures each of them represents five
different values of B. So the thing to
look at is what happens at the end
of these each of these plots after after
uh 20 time instance have passed. Are
these nine plots any different towards
the end or are they all identical in the
trailing bit? What do you guys think?
Are they different or are they all the
same? They're all identical, right? So,
what does that tell you? Is what is now
this value at the end
is what is being remembered? Is that a
function of the input?
The value that's being remembered, is it
a function of the input?
No. It doesn't matter what x0 was,
right? Is it a function of the weights,
the W's? No. The only thing that is
remembered is the bias. Is that good
behavior?
Is that what you want out of recurrence?
Nope. Right? That's with sigmoid. Here
is something with tanh. The thing with a
sigmoid is that it saturates within
three or four time steps very quickly.
With tanh, it's the same plot. You will
see I won't spend much time on it except
for the special case of all W and Z B
being zero. The plots are going to be
very much the same except that in this
case what is remembered as a function of
both W and B but not of the input. The
difference being that in that the time
it takes to get to the saturation
useless value is somewhat longer than
for a sigmoid. Which is why in recurrent
neural networks we you typically use
tanh as the activation in the recurrent
layers because they hold things in their
memory for some time more than uh the
sigmoid.
This is what you get with the the relu.
Now the relu is basically a linear
activation
meaning things will either blow up or
just go to zero. They're not it's not
going because it's a linear activation,
right? So if the principal value is
greater than one, it's going to blow up.
If the principal value is less than one,
it's going to be zero. And so the is not
a very nice activation either. In every
case, what we find is what is being
remembered is what what is being input
is no longer remembered. It blows up or
dies in a manner that depends only on
the network parameters and not on the
input.
So that was for these are scalar
recursions. So I have similar plots for
vector recursions where now w is a
vector. The input is a uh I think a 10
component vector. So here I have two
different uh I have two different
inputs. Here x0 is all ones. Here x0 is
all minus1's. And the maximum value of w
is 1.1. And I have a bias term. And what
you will see and then I have uh three
different activations.
What you will see is that in all cases
what is being remembered at the end the
top plot and the bottom plot if you sort
of normalize out the uh vertical axis
the plots are kind of messy but if you
scale them right what you'll find is
that in both in all these pictures what
is remembered at the end does not depend
on whether the input was all ones or all
minus ones it only depends on the
weights and the binds. So this was when
the maximum value is 0.9. This is for
1.1. You find the same behavior. And so
the characteristic we end up with is
that uh these recurrent networks, they
don't really remember their input.
Their behavior depends on the bias and
the largest value of the recurrent
weight matrix. If the largest value is
greater than one, it's going to blow up.
If it's less than one, it's going to
die. And it doesn't depend on the input
at all. The rate at which things blow up
or die depend only on the parameters. So
if you want to do a formal stability
analysis, those of you who are
electrical engineers would be familiar
with the liabo functions and roots
criterion and so on p zero analysis.
Uh we don't need to go all through all
of that. The picture should have
conveyed the story. So the lesson here
is that while bipolar activations like
tanage hold things on in memory a bit
longer as you can see over here sigmoid
saturates really quickly the tanage
holds on to things a little longer.
Overall the memory behavior of these
networks depends on the igen values of
the recurrent weight matrix and the
bias. The best case memory is short.
After just a few steps, eventually
whatever it is you gave as an input is
going to be forgotten and the behavior
that you observe is going to depend only
on the parameters of the recurrent layer
of the network. Did that make sense to
all of you guys? Yes or no? Give me
thumbs up if it made sense.
Can I see say 20 thumbs ups considering
there are 160 people in class?
All right, great. And so yes, time for
Paul too. The attendance has gone down
from 200 to 180 to 160. So today we'll
be posting all the attendances.
I might have failed to mention early in
the class and semester that I choose
which lectures I will decide to use to
mark your final attendance.
And u I can be random about it. So it
might be today's lecture.
15 seconds, guys.
I give you five more since lot of
reading.
All right. So, let me end this.
What is the answer to the first
question?
1 2 and three. What about the second
So,
how many time steps an RNN can retain
some memory of an input? depends on the
weights, depends on the bias, depends on
the activation function used, but it
does not depend on what it is. It's what
that's being remembered. Similarly, uh
what it remembers also depends on the
weights, bias, and activation, but not
the actual thing that that is you're
trying to remember. Is this desirable
behavior
or is this nasty?
It's not the right thing. This is not
what you want, right? And so here's the
story so far that you guys were looking
for. Recurrent networks retain
information from the infinite past in
principle. In practice, they tend to
blow up or forget. If the largest value
of the recurrent weight matrix is
greater than one, the network's response
may blow up. If it is less than one, the
response dies very quickly. The memory
of the network also depends on the
activation of the hidden units. Sigmoid
activations saturate and the network
becomes unable to retain new information
very quickly. ReLU activations blow up
or vanish rapidly. Tanh activations are
slightly more effective at storing
memory, but still not for very long. So
RNNs are excellent models for time
series analysis. In principle, they're
good for time series prediction,
classification, sequence generation.
They can even simplify problems that are
difficult for NLPs, but the memory isn't
all that great.
But then here's another problem,
something that we all you know and love.
The vanishing gradient problem. What is
it?
When you're trying to train deep
networks, any deep network, not just
regular networks, the gradient of the
error with respect to weights is
unstable. What do I mean? So here's a
network. If I can have an arbitrary
number of layers, and we know that the
output is a is basically a nested
function. It's the first layer is a
function of the input. the second layer
is a function of the second first layer
the third layer of is a function of the
second layer and so on and then finally
you comput a divergence of the between
the output of the network and the
desired output. If I were to draw draw
the influence diagram for this the input
influences the first aine value and the
derivative over here is just going to be
the weight of the first layer. The
alphine value influences the output of
the first layer and the derivative here
is going to be the jacobian of this
activation.
This guy influences the z over here and
that and the derivative on the edge is
going to be the weight over here. This z
influences f_sub_2 and the derivative
here is going to be the jacobian of this
activation and so on. So is this picture
making sense to all of you guys? This
guy.
Now when I begin computing my
derivatives backwards, if I want to
compute the derivative of D with respect
to X, what will I do? I first compute
the derivative of D with respect to F3,
which is this guy, right? Then from this
I compute the derivative with respect to
this guy. How do I do this? How do I
compute the derivative of D with respect
to Z3 given the derivative with respect
to F3? What do I do, guys?
We've done this many times. What do I
do?
Chain rule, right? But what is the chain
rule? What do I do exactly?
I multiply. I write multiply by the
Jacobian. Correct? Then when I take it
back from here, what do I do now?
What do I do? I write multiply by the
weight and then I write multiply by the
Jacobian. And I write multiply by the
weight and so on. So is this making
sense to everybody?
Okay. And so here's where we are, right?
And so here we are, right? For this very
deep network, the derivative of any of
the output of any layer with respect to
the divergence with respect to the
output of any layer is the derivative
for the output times the Jacobian of the
output layer times the weight of the
output layer times the Jacobian of the
penultimate layer and so on. So this
all of these blue terms this guy is a
vector right because the divergence is a
scalar the output is a vector so this
guy is a vector these jacobians and
weights they're all matrices yes or no
they're all matrices right okay and so
let's to analyze what happens to this we
just have to look at how these matrices
behave let's look at the jacobians first
now if I have a network of this kind
where each neuron in the hidden layer is
independent of every other neuron then
the Jacobian is going to be a diagonal
matrix for the recurrent layer.
Yes, you agree with this.
Okay. So we only need to understand what
the derivatives of the activation
functions in the recurrent layer look
like. So let's look at the derivative of
that of these guys. Here is what this is
the derivative of the sigmoid function.
We saw that the derivative of the
sigmoid function peaks at one and then
goes back to zero. Peaks at 0.25 and
the for the for the for the sigmoid it
peaks at 0.25. For the tanh it peaks at
one. And for the relu the derivative
looks like this, right? It's either zero
or one. You remember these guys?
Yes. No. Yes. Can I see like 20 thumbs
ups that you remember these?
Okay. That means each of these terms
is either one or less than one. Correct?
Yes or no?
So if I multiply a vector by this
matrix, what will happen to the length
of the vector? Is it going to increase
or is it going to decrease?
What will happen? It's going to shrink
because every component is being
multiplied by a number that's either one
or less than one, right? And so each one
of these matrices is going to shrink the
divergence,
the the derivative of the divergence.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Okay, that leaves us with these weight
matrices, right? Now, weight matrices
have this property. Any weight matrix
can be written using singular value
decomposition as W equals U SRpose
where S is the matrix of singular
values. It's going to be a diagonal
matrix with the singular values. And
when I multiply a ve vector by the
weight matrix, the length of the vector
is going to increase in the direction
where the singular values are greater
than one and it's going to decrease in
the directions where the singular value
is less than one. Furthermore, if I take
any arbitrary weight matrix and I plot
the singular values, you will find a
very small number of singular values
that are actually large. Most of them
are going to be really small. So the
majority of the singular values 90 99%
of the singular values are going to be
less than one which means that the
probability that any odd vector that you
pick will be in a direction with these
larger singular values is really very
small. And so what happens is that if I
just consider these weight matrices,
repeated multiplying by the
multiplication by the weight matrix is
going to increase
the derivative in the directions with
singular values greater than one. Shrink
it in directions where the singular
values are less than one. So the
repeated multiplication will either
result in either an exploding or a
vanishing gradient. That make sense to
everybody?
Yes. No, everybody. I'd like to see like
20 thumbs ups.
I'm still at 10.
All right. Okay. But you don't really
want to be considering just the weights
and the jacobians independently. You
actually want to be considering a layer
wise, which is the product of the
Jacobian and the weight.
And that two is a matrix. And so what
you're going to find is that this
derivative
is going to either expand in the
directions where these guys have
singular values greater than one and
shrink where they have less than less
than one. But the thing is that each of
these layers is different. So a
direction in which this guy has a
singular value greater than one is not
necessarily going to be the same as the
direction in which this guy has a
singular value greater than one. So the
net result is that the number of
components that will actually increase
is very small because somewhere in
between in fact for the majority of the
layers you're going to align with
singular values less than one and so the
overall derivative is going to expand in
a very small number of directions if at
all and it's going to shrink in the
majority of the directions. Does that
make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Right? And so this is what happens.
Right? The gradients in the earlier
layers can explode. But this will happen
to a very small number of entries.
Mostly they will vanish. And so and the
problem gets worse as the network depth
increases because the number of terms
you multiply keeps increasing.
This is the vanishing and exploding
gradient problem. Here's an example.
This was for an emnest model. It's a 19
layer MNEST model and each layer had
1,024 units. So I'm just plotting the uh
the uh activations at each of the uh the
derivatives at each of these units. The
derivative of the loss. This is at
initialization where the derivatives are
largest.
Everything has ELU activation and and
I'm looking looking at this over a
batch. This is the output layer. What do
we see? You see that as you go back
through the layers, all the derivatives
pretty much vanish by the time you get
halfway through the network. This is for
an ELO activation. This is for a relu
activation. The derivatives vanished
even faster. This is for a sigmoid. The
deriv derivatives are gone in just three
layers. This is for batch gradients.
This is for tanage. The derivatives
vanish quickly. Right? So, uh this was
for batches. What about individual
instances? Once again, you're going to
see the same thing. You're going to see
that in almost all cases,
the derivatives
are if you don't apply activations, then
you're dependent only on the weights,
you have the same behavior, right?
Because if I have a sequence series of
layers without activations, I can
collapse them all into a single layer.
If you don't have nonlinear activations
between two layers, the two layers
become one layer. So
basically this is what happens right.
What we find is that elude activations
maintain gradients longest but in all
cases the gradients effectively vanish
after about 10 layers. Both batch
gradients and gradients for individual
instances disappear. In reality if you
look closely you'll find a small number
of very bright spots that are not
visible because something has to account
for the change. And so other than that,
most of the derivatives just go to zero.
That make sense? This problem of
vanishing gradients to everybody.
Can I see some thumbs ups?
Like 20 of them. Okay, fine. And so
here's your favorite story so far.
Recurrent networks retain information
from the infinite past in principle and
practice the accurate memorization. The
hidden outputs can lower or shrink to
zero depending on the igen values of the
recurrent weight matrix. The memory is
also a function of the activation of the
hidden units. Tanh activations are the
most effective at retaining memory, but
they don't hold it for very long. Deep
networks also suffer from a vanishing or
exploding gradient problem. The gradient
of the error at the output gets
concentrated into a small number of
terms in the earlier layers and moves to
zero for others.
How does this do? What does this have to
do with recurrent neural networks? Well,
as we saw, recurrent neural networks are
really very, very, very deep networks.
And so, you're going to get bitten by
the vanishing gradient problem as well.
Recurrently, your networks not only have
the vanishing gradient problem when
you're trying to train them, you also
have, as we saw earlier, the problem
that uh the even in the forward pass,
things get forgotten very quickly.
something that goes in here either blows
up or is forgotten by the time you get
three steps out. So
you have all of these issues that in the
forward pass things can die or vanish
depending on the weights and the
activation. In the backward pass things
can die or van or or blow up depending
on the igon values the singular values
or the igon values of the jacobian
matrix of the activation and the
singular values of the weight matrix
basically on depending on the activation
and the weight matrix. So here is a
uh
pro mana. So long as you keep repeatedly
applying activations and weights, you're
going to have vanishing variance.
We have solutions around it. One of them
is to ensure that the weights matrix
always has a singular
singular values greater than one. That's
what a reset does
and
workounds. But this is what happens with
generic case.
5 seconds guys.
Okay. Give me 10.
All right, let me end this.
Okay,
first question. Which are the correct
statements?
Which are the true statements for the
first question, guys?
All
Second one.
Let's see. You're right. Right. The
derivatives for most most parameters
will become vanishingly small as we back
propagate the loss gradient through deep
networks. The derivatives for a small
number of parameters may blow up and
become large. The derivatives would be
more stable if the recurrent weight
matrices had singular values all equal
to one. And if the rec recurrent
activations were identity transforms,
right? Same thing with the memory,
right? The memory would be more stable
if the recurrent activations were
identity transforms and it would be more
stable if the recurrent weight matrix
were an identity matrix. Right? So that
sets the stage. The problem we have is
that the mere presence of weights,
matrices, and activations in the
recurrent layer causes it to have un
undesirable memory behavior and
undesirable behavior when it comes to
training.
What I mean by undesirable memory
behavior is that how long it remembers
something doesn't depend on what it is
trying to remember. It depends on the
parameters of the network. But then in
real life that's not how you want things
to behave. Let's say you're analyzing
some code. You're using some recurren
neural network to analyze code. If you
were analyzing this nested loop,
when you see this open curly brace, you
want to remember that you have
encountered an open curly brace until it
is closed. And you have no idea when
it's going to be closed. You can't say,
"Okay, I'm going to remember this for 20
time instance or four time instance. It
doesn't really make sense, right? You
have to remember it until you get the
signal that it's okay to forget it. And
that is not going to happen with the
usual recurrent neural network. That
make sense to everybody that statement?
Yes or no?
Can I see some thumbs ups? Yeah.
Seven. Eight. Come on.
Okay. All right. That's 19. Oh, 21.
Beautiful. And so, how do we solve that?
the domain of mystery and magic. Here's
what we have, right? The mere presence
of these weight matrices causes grief.
How can we solve for it?
The fact that there are weight matrices
causes memory problems, right? How can
we solve for that? Anybody
remove them? Sure. Right.
The presence of activation functions
causes grief. How can we solve for that?
You know, just the fact that we have
activation functions cause things to be
forgotten and derivatives to disappear
going back, right? So, how can we solve
for that? Anybody
give me a hack answer. What would you
do? Also, remove them, right? Let's just
get rid of them. These are nasty things.
We don't want them, right? So we want to
have a network that remembers
arbitrarily long to be recalled on
demand and not be dependent on the
vagaries of the network parameters. It
should be dependent on the inputbased
determination of whether something still
needs to be retained or not. And so
we're going to replace these things.
Yes, Edward. The weight matrices, their
igon values, if they're not all equal to
one, it's going to cause blow up or
vanishing. The activation functions,
their jacobians, all cause shrinking,
right? And so they cause things to be
forgotten going forward and vanish going
backwards. So let's get rid of them,
right? Let's replace these with
something that doesn't fade or blow up.
We're going to construct a network that
retains useful memory arbitrarily long
based on an input b you know using an
input based determination of whether
things must be remembered or not. So
you're going to retain memories until a
switch based on the info input flags
them as okay this is okay to forget. So
what does that look like? You start off
by putting things in memory and then
every subsequent input is analyzed and
based on what you see from it you modify
the memory. If this says this is not you
know if I've seen initial curly brace as
things come in this remembers a curly
brace and then maybe this got a hash and
says no nothing to be done so it
continues to remember the curly brace.
This saw an I it says nothing to be done
it continues to remember the curly
brace. This saw close curly brace you
say okay forget. So you're going to
modify what's in the memory based on a
determination that analyzes that
analyzes the input.
This is how we're going to model the
memory. Did this make sense to
everybody?
Does this make sense to everybody? And
so that's I see one. Yes. Okay.
That's what we're going to do. This is
what we call the constant error
corrosive. Something in memory just goes
through. There are no weights. There are
no activations. They just keep going on.
But then you have this multiplicative
term that modifies it after each input.
This multiplicative term is called a
gate. So, and this thing sees here's
pattern one. This guy says, have I seen
pattern two? Nope. Continue. Have I seen
pattern two? Nope. Continue. And so on.
But this has no nonlinearity in it
anymore. But for neural networks to
work, you need nonlinearities. And so
you have other portions of the work that
perform the nonlinear nonlinear tasks.
Neurons that compute the workable state
from the memory. And how does this gate
itself work? This guy actually looks at
the input to determine if this thing
must be modified. But it's not
sufficient to look at the input. It must
also look at what's already in memory.
Right? There's no point in my saying
forget this open brace if there's no
open brace in the memory. And so this
gate is going to take the input and
what's already in memory
as its inputs to determine how to modify
what's in memory.
And it can take other context stuff. For
example, if it's if it's a curly brace,
if this encounters a curly brace and it
sees a curly brace, it still shouldn't
say forget it. if that curly brace
actually occurred in a comment section,
this guy is going to tell you no, you're
this is not the right thing. And so this
is the uh this extra stuff set the
context. And of course uh this you don't
want to just look at the nonlinearly
modified state. You also want to
directly look at the memory itself. And
so this is the overall structure of the
network where the whatever is in memory
gets modified by gates which determine
the modification by looking at
considering the input what's already in
memory and external context. Did this
make sense to everybody?
Yes. Now
can I see like 20 yeses
because this is the crux of
All right, 17 18. Come on, guys. You're
sort of struggling to give me the 20.
People have fallen asleep. Can you just
give me the 20 yeses, thumbs ups, and
then you know, let's move on.
I'm guessing not. Okay, let's say.
So, this is our long shortterm memory.
You explicitly latch information to
prevent DKO blow up. In the remaining
slides, I borrowed from this
cola.github.io
for my pictures. Here's your standard
recurrent network, not the LST, the
standard recurren network. In the
standard recurren network, if you think
of this like we like to think of these
as cells within a recurrent cell, the
past hidden state comes in, the current
hidden state comes in. These two are
combined
to compute the new hidden state which
goes into the higher layers of the
network and also into the future. So do
you guys see how this is the standard
recurren network? I'm going to use
similar pictures everywhere. The hidden
state depends on the hidden state at the
previous time and the current input.
Right? So this is your standard
recurrent
neuron. In an LSTM, this cell becomes a
lot more complex. This is what it looks
like.
And again, remember, every line
represents a vector. But let's let's
break it down. It's not not as hard as
it looks. This guy is what we call a
constant error corros. This is the
memory line that I showed earlier. It
has no weights. It has no activations.
It's a remembered cell state. It's the
memory which gets only modified by
external signals.
So that's the constant error corrosion,
right? It carries information through
only affected by a gate and addition of
history which is also gated. Now it's
nice to think of it, you know, use this
curly braces as an example. I can have
this memory line tracking the number of
open braces that I have encountered in a
piece of code. So anytime I've seen an,
you know, I can keep adding open braces.
Every time I see a a an appropriate
close brace, then I have to decre
decrement what's in memory. If I see a
new open brace, I have to increment
what's in memory. So there are two
different operations, right? One of them
is looking for for closed curly braces
to decrement the memory. The other is
looking for open curly braces to
increment the memory. Do you guys see
that? They're two different things.
Yes. No.
So this gu is remembering these. I want
to forget it if I see this. I want to
increment it if I see this. Right? So I
have two distinct operations. One for
forgetting and one for incrementing. And
to break the symmetry, one of them is
multiplicative and one of them is
additive. This make sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Give me thumbs ups if it made
sense.
I've stopped being greedy. I I'll take
I'll take 10 thumbs ups.
20 didn't seem to work.
Okay.
And so
what are these gates then? Right. The
gates are simple sigmoid units with
outputs in the range 0 to one which
controls how much of the information is
to be led through. This first guy is
what we call a forget gate. So this guy
is remembering what's in memory. This
might encounter a pattern which says you
must decrement what's in memory and then
gives it gives it a signal a
multiplicative signal between zero and
one to reduce decrement what's in
memory. It's called a forget gate. It
operates on what the nonlinear hidden
state and the input.
Then this is the incrementer.
Here you're going to say did I see a new
curly open curly brace. This tanh is a
pattern detector. So this is going to
say increment the the memory. But then
it's not enough to simply look determine
that you saw an open curly brace. You
also want to make sure that it's right.
If it happens to be in a comment
section, you don't want to be
incrementing it. So you have an
additional term which is a gate which
kind of looks at the context and decides
whether this information must be passed
on or not. So there are two terms here.
Something called an input gate. This guy
was a forget gate. Here you have an
input gate and an input pattern
detector. And what actually goes through
is the product of the two. This make
sense to everybody.
Yes. No.
Okay. Okay. And the final operation.
So what comes in in the memory is first
multiplied by what's what the forget
great sends through to decrement counts
if necessary
and then incremented by what this
combination sends through to increment
counts if necessary.
So ct equals forget* ctus 1 plus it * c
where ct delta t is the output of the
pattern detector. This makes sense to
everyone? Yes. No.
Okay,
easy, right? And then of course the
output you have to apply something
nonlinear to it. So we actually pass it
through tanh for the reason that you
know tanh is the best activation for
uh for uh recurren networks. But then
even so we actually also include another
gate to determine if what's currently in
the memories or is is usable in the
current state. And this gate looks at at
the current context which is the
previous hidden state value and the
input. And just to make things complete
you also look at what's already in raw
memory rather than just this nonlinearly
transformed hidden state. And so this is
the complete long short-term memory
unit. Did the entire unit make sense to
you guys?
>> Yes or no?
>> Uh, Professor
>> Yes.
>> So um for the uh I forgot what it's
called the um the top bar the
>> that this is the memory line the
constant error.
>> Yeah. Yeah. that the CC why do we send
the input through it twice like we send
it after
um it
>> we say no so we have two distinct
operations that's it one is a decrement
one is an incremental
>> and then after that we also after it
goes to the t we also send it through
there as well
>> no no so so this remember there's no
nonlinearity over here at all right
>> something without nonlinearity is not
very useful in a neural network so we
pull it put it we Don't apply
nonlinearities here because we know that
if you put any nonlinearity here, it
kills the memory behavior. We pull the
nonlinearity off on the side.
>> That answer,
>> right?
>> Yeah. Yeah, that makes sense. Thank you.
>> Right. So that's what we do. And so
here is your final poll.
I can
15 seconds, guys.
Okay,
let me end this right here.
What are the answers
or
I think all left sick.
Wait, what happened to mine?
Oh, man.
Yes, all of them are right. LSTM
stabilize the memory by eliminating the
problematic recurrent reads and
activations. They update the memory
based on patterns detected in the input
in the current context of what they
already remember.
In the absence of external cues, they
can remember a pattern forever because
in the absence of external cues, this
guy is always going to give you a one.
Just keep going. Ideally, this guy is
going to give you a zero. you know,
nothing to be added and it's just going
to keep going on
the answer by piece,
right? And so they're suited to building
pattern analyzers requiring long-term
memory, eg code parsers that can verify
if an open brace has been properly
closed.
And so here is the complete sequence of
operations. First you compute an input
gate, a forget gate which is this guy.
Then you compute this input gate which
is this guy. Then you compute the
pattern detector which is this guy.
And then you update this guy by
multiplying it by the forget gate and
then adding the output of the pattern
detector.
Then you compute the output gate which
is this guy and this is passed through
the tanh and multiplied by the output
gate. Right? So this is the sequence of
operations that happens inside an LSTM.
And you can see forget gate input gate
pattern detector update C output gate
and the actual nonlinear
u variant of the hidden state. So I have
some pseudo code here just to show you
how the whole thing works. Now in a
recurrent network, a recurrent cell
simply computed an aine value and
applied an activation function to it. In
a standard recurrent network in an LSTM,
that little recurrent unit has become a
much more complex operator, what we will
call an LSTM cell. So at each there's a
new copy of the LSTM cell at each time
in each layer. and you're assuming that
the LSTM cell maintains all the retains
all the local variables that are not
relevant to the global computation but
are only relevant to that cell. So
here's what the the LSTM cell would look
like. It's going to take as input the
what's in currently in the memory and
the non the nonlinearly transformed
version of it. the current input and any
parameters. It's going to output the
modified memory and the modified
nonlinearly transformed version of the
uh what's in memory. And so the actual
computation first you compute the aine
term for the forget gate apply an
activation the sigmoid to compute that
forget gate. You compute the aphine term
for the input gate and apply a sigmoid
to compute the value for the input gate.
compute the aine term for the pattern
detector. Use the tanage activation to
compute the determine if the pattern's
been found. And then you modify what's
in memory by forget times the currency
plus input gate times the pattern.
Compute the aphine term for the output
gate and then apply sigmoid activation
to it. And the nonlinear version of
what's in memory is obtained by
multiplying O by
the by the tanh activation modified
memory. Right? So once this cell is
computed
the recurren network itself looks just
like before. The hidden state at time
zero is just the input and then the
layer zero is just the input. You go
through time at each time you go through
the layers but within each layer you're
not simply computing the standard LSTM
you know a fine plus activation you
actually compute the LSTM cell where the
LSTM cell obtains as input the H and the
C values from the previous time and the
H values from the lower layer along and
to compute the output C and H. So did
all of this make sense guys?
Yes or no? All of this makes sense.
So, give me 10 thumbs ups. I'll move on.
>> All right.
>> Okay. Fine.
So, training an LSTM is like training a
regular LST RNN with one difference.
Uh you're going to define a sequence
divergence and back propagate it through
time. as before. The difference is that
instead of back propagating through an
RNN unit, you're going to back propagate
through an LSTM set. And this is
devilishly hard. So let's look at how
the derivative of the divergence with
respect to CT minus one with you know
happens right with respect to CT not Ct
out here right. So if I want to compute
the derivative of the divergence with
respect to this guy what are all the
paths through which CT connects to the
divergence? Here's this path. It
connects through HT. Here's this path
through this gate where it goes through
HT. Here's this path which goes straight
through CTUS one. Here is this path
which go loops around like so. And then
here is this path. And I can keep adding
more and more paths. So the total number
of paths through which CT is dependent
the divergence depends on CT is really
long you know is is large and trying to
compute the derivatives explicitly is
going to be a bit of a pain.
So similarly if I want to compute the
derivative for say ht
there's the path that comes straight
down from the top there's this path
there's this path there's this path
there's this path and so on right so as
you can see from these slides if you
want to actually explicitly capture all
the dependencies
required to compute the derivative
writing the formula down is going to be
really really hard that make sense to
everybody
Yes. No.
So what do you do in this case?
What do we do in this case guys?
What did we do for CNN's?
Let's go through the code. Let's invert
the code. Right? So here I'm not going
to explicitly derive the derivatives.
For those of you who feel, you know,
evil towards yourself, you can try to
work it out.
But then let's look at the pseudo code.
Let's look at the code. Right? Here is
the forward code. You first computed the
aphine term for the forget gate then the
forget gate. Then the aine term for the
input gate then the input gate. The aine
term for the pattern detector. The
pattern detector. The updated memory.
The aine term for the output gate. Then
the output gate and then the nonlinearly
transformed h memory. If I'm back
propagating, in which order would I
compute the derivatives?
Top to bottom or bottom to top? How
would I do this,
guys?
How would I back propagate this? Anyone?
Bottom to top. So, here's what I'm going
to do. I'm going to start at the bottom.
When I'm coming back, I'm going to have
the derivative for H0. Right? So, the
derivative for there are two terms to
the right, O and C 0. So the derivative
of O is simply the derivative of H0 *
tan H. The derivative for tan H of C 0
is simply the derivative of 4 *
derivative of 80 * R. So did these two
make sense.
I got I just inverted this term, right?
And then the derivative for C 0 is just
the you know I'm just going to multiply
what I had here. d tanh c 0 by the
derivative for the tanh activation
function itself. Then I take a step
back.
The output gate was sigmoid of z0.
Right? At this point I have the
derivative for zero because it has been
uh the derivative for o because it has
been computed out here. So the
derivative of for z0 is d o times the
derivative of the sigma. Then I go back
the previous operation was this guy. At
this point I have the derivative for Z
zero. From those I can compute the
derivatives for each of these seven
terms.
Then I can take a step back. So so I
have all of it. Then I can take a step
back. The pre the previous operation was
this guy. By now I have the derivative
for C 0. From this I can compute the
derivatives for each of these four
terms.
And so I can literally just work my way
backwards one line at a time. and write
out all the derivatives and in the end
I'm going to get the derivatives for my
parameters and the inputs to the cell.
Did this make sense to everybody?
The process that I just followed.
Yes. No. Guys,
we have a very nice handout that's on
the course website. How to compute a
derivative. Take a look at it. Right.
See, you're computing derivatives of
you're not you're not changing C. You're
computing all derivatives going
backwards. Okay?
And so this was your forward
computation. The backward computation is
going to look much the same except now
you're flowing derivatives back through
the network. I won't go through the
pseudo code. Take a look at it. But it's
actually very simple when you understand
the code. And just to make sure that you
guys actually understand it, we're going
to make you work through it for your
homework. So that's with the LSTM.
But then an LSTM looks unnecessarily
complex. There are lots of crazy things
and so you're likely to ask why. And so
there have been many variants of the
LSTM that try to simplify it a bit to
address this question of why. One of
them is the gated recurrent unit.
Some of the simplifications it says that
if you're going to forget something then
you're you're not going to increment it.
If you're going to use some input
pattern to increment what's in memory,
it's obviously not necessarily useful
for forgetting. They're two different
things. And so you use one gate and you
do one minus this gate for forgetting
and the gate value for incrementing. So
you combine these two into a single
gate. Second, there's no need for me to
carry both the C and the H as I do over
here. Instead, I can just compute the H
from the C on the fly as I'm going
forward in time. So once again, the
nonlinear operation occurs on the fly.
And this gives you the gated recurrent
unit. We're going to write code for it.
So you so so you will see more of it.
You can design your own uh variance for
the LSTM cell if you so desire.
And as far as the architecture is
concerned, it's going to be just like
your standard recurrent neural network
except now each of these boxes is now an
LSTM cell or a GRU cell or whatever
variant you yourself design. Did all of
this make sense? I went over it a little
fast, but it's the same thing. I mean,
it's uh fairly simple. That make sense?
Okay. And of course you can use this in
birectional networks right because in
biirectional networks these cells are
now going to be LSTM cells or GRU cells
if that's what you use otherwise
everything else remains the same
and so
the story so far
recurrent networks are poor at
memorization
memory can explode or vanish depending
on the weights and the activation
They also suffer from the vanishing
gradient problem during training. The er
error at any time cannot affect
parameter updates in the two distant
past because of the vanishing gradient
problem. So for example, seeing a closed
bracket cannot affect the network's
ability to predict an open bracket if it
happened to remember an open bracket if
it happened too long ago in the input.
This is for your standard RNA. So LSTMs
and are an alternative formalism where
memory is made more directly dependent
on the input rather than network
parameters and structure through a
constant error corrosal memory structure
with no weights or activations. For
instance, it has direct switching and
increment decrement from pattern
recognizers.
It doesn't suffer from a vanishing
gradient problem.
But because things can keep incrementing
in it, it can indeed suffer from an
exploding gradient problem. And that's
something that we have to worry about.
And so that's I mean there are other
issues once we have come up with these
basic ideas.
The real issue is that you're actually
computing divergences between sequences
and sequences and that introduces
complications
and we will see how to deal with those
you know one example of those
complications and how to deal with them
in the next couple of classes. So that's
the end of today's lecture. First, did
all of this make sense?
Give me thumbs ups. And this time I'm
hoping to see 30 or 40 thumbs ups
because class is over.
Okay. Now let me answer your questions.
Sean, how do we know the forget gate
does the forgetting and the inca?
So the it has to do with the fact that
this is a multiply and this is an add.
So you break the symmetry by having
different operations.
Whether they actually forget and
increment, we don't know. But they're
going to be doing different things. That
answer your question, Sean,
right? That's why they're not both
multipliers. They are different
operations to break the symmetry.
Any other question?
There was one earlier, right? Which was
recurrence has chosen to use past chosen
to remember past values.
Exactly.
works. Your conventional recurrent
network has this problem. It's supposed
to remember stuff, but it's really
crappy at it, which is why we use the we
modified it to the LSTM structure. That
answer your question?
Yeah. Okay. So, Sean, no guarantee,
right? It's all eventually unsupervised.
We just impose this inductive bias on
the model saying, you know, let's have
all of these components and hope
hopefully it learns the right thing. But
there's no explicit guarantee, right?
That answer your question, Sean.
So,
okay,
I will. Any other questions?
Does the LSTM's architecture effectively
so efficiently solve the memory problem
or does it introduce? No, it has
instabilities,
but it does solve the memory problem to
a great extent. It doesn't solve it
fully, but instead of being 10 time
steps of memory, it goes into many
hundreds of time steps or often longer.
So, anytime you use recurrent networks,
you never use a vendor recurrent network
anymore. You always use the STS or their
variance
where we stuck the recording.